Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 4 -- Letters to Franklin 1779 January-November Mss.B.F85inventory04
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Magellan (Magalhaens), Jean-Hyacinthe de. London
    At the author's request, sends him the latest philosophical work of Dr. Priestley. Concerning Miller's Botanical Collection, a work which has been carried into execution by Dr. Fothergill, who desired that, through Franklin, it might be forwarded to the Philosophical Society at Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de. L'Orient
    Thinks Franklin ought to see the French and American fleet riding at anchor and give them his benediction before they sail; judges they need it from the disputes prevailing among the officers on board the "Alliance" and "Bon Homme Richard"; discusses the chance of finding parallels for such behavior in ancient history; thinks that veneration for Franklin is the chief reason of France's devotion to America; is tired enough of trying to reconcile these Americans and supply their numerous wants.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    Arrival of the "Alliance," "Sensible" and "Pallas"; impossible to say when the little armament will be ready to sail; suggestions as to the best time for the Marquis [de la Fayatte] to leave Paris. Asks Franklin's advice concerning the bestowal of American commissions on the Captains of various vessels, and the best manner of wording them. Misunderstandings among the officers on board the "Alliance"; hears that the first lieutenant threatens to leave the ship; this will mean a breach of discipline, but little loss to the service; recommends that a sufficient number of officers be properly authorized to hold courts-martial, simply as a means to "keep little minds in proper awe."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Adams, John. L'Orient
    Trusts that the Chevalier de la Luzerne is aware of the value of every moment in expediting their voyage to America; thinks the chances of getting safe into port are ten times greater at Boston than Philadelphia; concerning the transportation of the Chevalier's baggage; sends his regards to various ladies, for whose characters he has a great respect.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779?] May 14; A.L.S 2p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Sends a note on the military services of M[ajor] Pierre F[rancois de] Boy, of Marseilles, who wishes to re-enter the service of the United States. Hopes soon to return to Passy and be Franklin's neighbor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. L'Orient
    All his officers have conspired against him; would rather give up his command than endure longer such a condition of affairs; his first lieutenant desires to leave the ship; told him he could not without Franklin's order.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779.] May 15; A.L.S. in 3d P. 1p.; Diriks, Colonel J.G. Paris
    Desiring to send some letters to Boston by the first opportunity.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Sending Frankllin a Congress commission and warrant which he may want for Capt. Jones. Report of a spanish fleet bound for Brest. General [Nathanael] Greene's goods ready to place on board the "Three Friends," under convoy of the "Alliance"; wishes to know if Capt. Jones and the "Alliance" go together.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Maximilen Henri, Marquis de Saint Simon. Utrecht
    Le Comte de Sarsfield gave him reason to hope that Franklin would examine the notes which he left with him, and which are such an important factor in his proposed work. Prophesies the outcome of the war in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Wharton, Samuel. Paris
    Has sent a parcel of papers about Vandalia, of which it may be proper Franklin should have a copy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 16; A.L.S. 3p.; Arendt, Baron d'
    The results of his observations at the German Court and his frequent conferences with the Minister; does not think the Court will declare the independence of America, or sign a treaty of commerce, or send vessels to America; their disposition, however, very favorable; their willingness to open their ports to American vessels; his ability to push the matter, if he had been furnished with proper authority; desires to know if he is to come to Paris or to await the return of Mr. Lee; if he cannot be use in Europe, will return to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Boyer, -----. Paris
    Desiring Franklin to seal the enclosed letter and forward it in his next packet.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 16; A.L.S. 1p.; DuMont, -----. Paris
    Enclosing tickets for the meeting of the Society of Emulation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 16; A.L.S 3p.; Duffield, Benjamin. Bordeaux
    Aware that he has disgraced Franklin's introduction. Expressing great penitence for his past follies and indiscretions; has purchased his experience dearly; has been shut out from his parents and all that he holds dear; desires to enter the army of his countrymen; kindness of Mr. Conyngham, who has promised to procure him a passage to America; would rather get employment on board a privateer; his funds very low; desires Franklin to mark out a line of conduct for him which he promises to follow.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 17; A.L.S. 1p; Sayre, Stephen. Amsterdam
    Requesting letter of recommendation to the Governors of Martinique and Dominica, as he expects to set sail shorthly for those islands.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Morel,-----. Versailles
    At the suggestion of the Marquis de la Fayette, sends Franklin his work, "Le tableau des forces actuelles de la France."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Fort, Marc. Marseilles
    Acknowledging the part Franklin took in helping them to recover damages for the ship "L'Élégante" and her cargo; desire him to recommend thier agent, M. Antoine Gautier, to the Magistrates a Williamsburg, that they may help him recover certain funds detained by Capt. Collinson of Bordeaux.
    (In French. In duplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 17; A.L.S 2p.; Adams, John. L'Orient
    Glad to hear that the Chevalier is making diligent preparations for his departure; will be happy to show him and his secretary the town to Boston, before they go to Philadelphia. Thinks he will not go to Congress very soon, unless ordered. Hopes the resolves of the States General will bring the English to reason; the late exchange of prisoners is the sole instance they have given of justice and humainty since the repeal of the Stamp Act; private letters from England say that the last proposals of Spain have been rejected with ill humor. The "Poor Richard" about ready to sail.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Enclosing a copy of his letter (2 p.) to the Grand Pensionnaire, relative to the capture and condemnation by an American privateer of a Dutch ship taken by mistake for English property. Necessity of strengthening the Anti-English party.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 19; A.L.S. 1p.; de Sainte Marie, Veuve Presle. Paris
    Thanking Franklin for his promise to forward the enclosed letters to her son in Guadeloupe.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Enclosing a letter from M. de Gimat with an account of a very dangerous division between the officers of the "Alliance." Sends Franklin his ideas for print; could make out an immense book on so rich a matter. Reflections on the English Ministry. Ireland's unsettled state; possibility of a corps of two thousand men with four thousand spare arms finding among the Irish many lovers of liberty and many enemies to the English government.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Protest against the Admiralty's evasive reply, by the merchants of Amsterdam and Rotterdam; their demand for unlimited convoys. England asked to revise certain verdicts in the case of Dutch vessels captured by the English. Lord Weymouth's refusal. Visit from Nicholas Davis.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Stockton, Samuel W. The Hague
    Owing to lack of funds, is unfortunately deprived of the pleasure of paying his respects to Franklin before leaving for America; desires to carry any despatches for Congress Franklin may care to send; begs for a few lines in his favor to the Committee of Congress for Foreign Affairs, as well as some letters of recommendation from Dr. Pringle; transcribes copies of letters written in his favor by Samuel Wharton and Mr. Cushing. Franklin's cautionary letter respecting Nicholas Davis has prevented the latter's imposing on several persons. Affairs in the Netherlands; the Prince of Orange again endeavoring to delay the equipment of the convoys; an attack on their convoys by the English needed to rouse the provinces from their lethargy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 21; A.L.S. 3p.; de la Torre, Isidoro. Cadiz
    Account of a Spanish vessel having been attacked by an American corsair and forced to pay a ransom; desires indemnity for the loss; has the necessary documents to prove his statements.
    (In Spanish.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Concerning the protested American bills of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Wynbergen, L.F. Baron Van. Wesel
    His military services in the Netherlands and Prussia; desirous of entering the American army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Jeanrenand, P. Geneva
    Begs for news of his son, to whom Franklin granted letters of recommendation to a friend in Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Morel, -----. Versailles
    Asks for some slight monetary return for the maps he sent to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Bocheron, -----. Rosny
    Is convinced that even a bagatelle in favor of the American cause is not a matter of indifference to Franklin, therefore sends a poem inspired and created by the love of liberty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Arrival of a small ship from Maryland. Encloses a petition from Joseph Bail[e]y and Philip Chapman, prisoners, taken on board a whaleman by the "Marquis de la Fayette." Probable destination of M. La Motte Picquet. The "Gen. Mercer," to sail about the 10th of June direct for Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 24; A.L.S. 4p.; Beaufort, — comte de. Liège
    Enclosing a plan and a set of conditions, in accordance with which he proposes to raise a body of troops for the service of America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 24; A.L.S. James Pinkerton et al. 2p.; The Crew of the Drake Sloop of War. Fougères
    Petition that the same aid which was rendered to that part of the crew which was exchanged, should be given themselves who are wounded and in the Brest Hosipital.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Jacques Rocquette, T.A. Elsevier, and Fréres Rocquette. Rotterdam
    Begging to be informed of the safe arrival of a packet, which they have just forwarded to Franklin. Inquire where they can negotiate American bank notes and whether the interest is payable annually.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Baudouin, -----. Paris
    Ashamed to left Franklin know the full extent of his thoughtlessness; promises it will not occur again.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Gillon, Alexander. Paris
    Desires Franklin's advice concerning the matters he wishes to lay before M. de Sartine, with whom he dines that day; importance of those matters which concerns the State of South Carolina.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Thinks that Franklin's paper on the "Aurora Borealis" having been read at the Royal Academy precludes its being heard at the Royal Society; hears, however, that Franklin is to favor them with a paper on a more useful subject; at the next meeting of the Council the matter of Franklin's copies will be taken up. Intends to retire to the country in order to finish his book on small-pox. Concerning his paper on a new method of suspending magnetic needles, as well as one on the nature and explosive force of gun powder; Dr. Priestley acknowledges in the latter case the inferiority of his theory.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Thanking Franklin for his goodness to his son; thinks him the finest little lad he ever saw. Has at last obtained the consent of the gentlemen to examine his accounts.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 26; L.S. 1p.; Sartine, Antoine-Raymond-Gualbert-Gabriel de. Versailles
    In receipt of the letter relative to the brigantine belonging to Mr. Giddings, Which was accidentally sunk by a battery off Guadeloupe; His Majesty willing to grant an indemnity commensurate with the loss.
    (In French. Copy.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    His keen disappointment at the change of plans on the part of the French Government; instead of the Marquis [de la Fayatte] joining him with troops, he is ordered elsewhere; considers no season would have been as fit for their purpose as the present.
    Printed in Hale's "Franklin in France," I, 258.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Brault and Demezaudré. St Malo
    Unfortunately, will not be able to profit by Franklin's good will, as Capt. Landais's destination is changed, and he says it is impossible to carry them to America; begs for Franklin's protection should another opportunity offer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    High opinion of de N[eufville]. Four Bostonians in town,—Messrs. Sears, Cordes, Coffin and Sayre; Sayre's apparent knowledge of financial affairs; his attitude toward de N[eufville]; desires Franklin's advice on this head. Desirability of Holland's being America's creditor. Criticism of the published letter concerning Capt. [James] Cook.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Torris, John. Dunkirk
    As the sole agent for the "Black Prince," will be very exact in advising Franklin of all particulars concerning the vessel. Informing him of Capt. Marchant's intention to capture, if possible, the British packets between Dover and Calais; desires to know if they would be deemed lawful prizes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Napier, James Lenox. Bayonne
    Writes on behalf of sixteen American prisoners, of whom he is one, who desire to be released and to go on board some ship bound for America; homesick for their country, their wives and their children.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Holtzendorff, Louis-Casimir, baron de. Paris
    Begging Franklin to forward the enclosed letters to the Carolinas; flatters himself that Congress, through Franklin's interposition, will at length do him the justice he merits; would be entirely ruined should they fail to comply with his just claims in accordance with their own resolves; has applied to the Comte de Vergennes to obtain his Most Christian Majesty's protection in the affair.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Walsh, John late Master of the Drake. Fougères
    Gratefully acknowledges Franklin's former humane interference on behalf of the English prisoners on board the "Patience" brig at Brest; obliged to renew his complaints owing to his harsh treatment by M. Riou of Brest, who ,from malicious motives, allowed the crew to be exchanged before the officers, against all established custom; begs to be sent to England with four of his remaining crew, and promises to do his utmost to get Americans exchanged in their places.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 28; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Jones, Sir William. Paris
    Presenting a translation of a pretended fragment of Polybius. He, as well as Mr. Paradise, will be glad to carry any messages or letters Franklin may care to send to England.
    Printed in works (Sparks, VIII, 365).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 29; L.S.; Wharton, Samuel. Paris
    Presenting facts relating to the seizure at Dieppe of the effects of Thomas and Robert Burdy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 31; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Wharton, Joseph Jr. Paris
    Returning American newspapers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 31; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Arrival of certain vessels from America; news of the English being defeated near Savannah. Is lodging at Mr. N.'s; for obvious reasons will not Chevalier G[ran]d nor his associates. Desires Franklin's advice before becoming more intimate with Mr. Sayre.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 31; A.L.S. 4p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. London
    Has just finished with the sheets [of his edition of his "Political, Miscellaneous and Philosophical Pieces," London, 1779], only that he has expectations of procuring his [Franklin's] preface to Mr. Gal[lo]way's speech, and in consequence the epitaph. Should have applied to Mr. Wharton for them before his leaving England. His great admiration of Franklin's paper on the "Aurora Borealis"; will send his comments on that subject later; concerning Franklin's paper on the "Vis Inertiae"; changes he expects to make in his own comments on that paper.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 May 31; A.L.S. 2p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Concerning the loan for America recommended to their care; Mr. Sayre spoke with judgement on this point, though he confessed he had no commission either from Congress or Franklin; begs him to recommend their firm to Congress or to any private acquaintance in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779? March 24]; L.S. 4p.; d'Auzéville, Gerard
    Begs Franklin to help him in carrying out his project of going to America and acquiring a small tract of land for cultivation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 1; L.S. in 3d P. 1p.; John Paradise and Sir William Jones. Paris
    Desiring Franklin to insert in the enclosed passport the fact that Mr. Paradise is an American gentleman, though born in Greece.
    Printed in Works (Sparks. VIII, 366).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, -----
    The dinner proposed for the morrow at Auteuil has been postponed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Petterellty, Lieut.-Col. Bregence
    Recommends his son, who wishes to quit the Imperial service in order to fight for the American cause. His dismissal was regretfully granted.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Verité, Capt. Hippolyte (Hyppolite) de. Olmütz
    His military record in Hungary; desires to enter the American army; has a wife and two children, whom he desires to take with him, should his offer be accepted.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 2; L.S. 1p.; Hardouin,-----. Paris
    Desiring to know if Franklin wishes to subscribe to the works of M. Charles Bonnet.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Bordot, François. La Rochelle
    The arrival of two English privateers, the "Defiance" and the "Ladies Resolution," taken by the frigate "l'Hermione"; slight resistance encountered; no loss of life; the crews, mostly boys, numbering 194, were sent to prison.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 3; Conway, Thomas. Paris
    Certifying to the excellent character and military zeal of M. de Santuary, who was made prisoner near Philadelphia, in November, 1777; the Congress desires to procure his exchange with an English officer of the rank of major.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Circa 1779.] June 3; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Sartine, Antoin de
    Received his letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 4; L.S. 1p.; Marat, Jean Paul (The Representative of author)
    Inviting Franklin to be present at dinner at the hotel of M. le Marquis de l'Ausbespine, together with Messieurs le Comte de Maillebois, de Montigni, LeRoy and Sage; desires also his grandson's company, who, if the weather keeps clear, will have an opportunity to see the experiments. If Franklin has perused the manuscript treatise on fire, begs him to give him his opinion thereupon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 5; L. in 3d P. 1p.; John Paradise and Sir William Jones. Calais
    Acknowledging Franklin's courtesy and hospitality to them, in the most cordial terms.
    Printed in works (Sparks, VIII, 366).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Decision of Committee appointed by the Holland Assembly to stand by the resolution in favor of unlimited convoys. Enclosing copy of a memoir [2 p.] presented by Sir J[oseph] Y[orke] to L[eurs] H[autes] P[uissances] complaining bitterly of the calumnies against England published in the Leyden Gazette and of one in especial put into the mouth of the Russian Minister, and demanding retraction and satisfaction. Arrival of M. [Conrad Alexandre] Gérard [de Rayneval]'s despatches from Philadelphia.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 June 5; A.L.S. Fra[nci]s Hopkinson. 1p.; The Treasurer of Loans. Philadelphia
    Notification of bills of exchange furnished to the State of Pennsylvania.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 5; A.L.S. 3p.; Schweighauser, John D. Nantes
    Account of expenditures for fitting out the frigate "Alliance" and the brig "Morris," and note of drafts drawn in discharge of those expenses.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 5; A.L.S. 1p; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    Is about to leave for a tour of inspection among the military schools of the kingdom; promises to keep him informed of any maritime news he may receive; sends messages from the Comtesse de Forbach to Franklin and his grandson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Circa 1779.] June 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Chaulnes, Duc de
    Desiring to know the title of a book on the transportation of timber in the Pyrenees; promised to procure it for Mr. Vaughan.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 7; A.L.S. 4p.; Sayre, Stephen. Amsterdam
    Once more requests letters of recommendation to the Governor of Martinique, Guadeloupe or Dominica. Surprised at Franklin's silence concerning the construction of a new kind of ship; is sure he can construct a ship far superior to any then in use; with a very few could render the whole British navy totally useless. Has received letters from London desiring to know how far and in what manner Franklin would give aid to Ireland; an American Commissioner needed in the matter; offers himself for the position. Lord North receives constant information of affairs in Paris, through one, Dr. Moore, an ex-clergyman and "a dirty fellow."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 7; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Ross, Jno. Paris
    Sending some American papers just arrived by a vessel from Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 7; A.L.S. 4p.; Evén, -----. Bannalec
    Offering his services to America; desires Franklin to procure him a passage to America; will trust to the justice of that country to establish himself.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Jacques Rocquette, T.A. Elsevier, and Fréres Rocquette. Rotterdam
    Enclose the two bills issued by the States of America, concerning which they desire information.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 June 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Peirce, Jeremiah. Tenterden
    A native of East Greenwich, Rhode Island; his capture by an English firgate, escape from Forton prison, enlisting on board a French cutter and his present wretched situation as a prisoner; begs Franklin to procure his exchange; enclosing certificates. [Endorsement by Mr. Thomas Viny, recommending Pierce as an honest fellow, to Franklin's kindness.]